<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An advice against libertinism shewing the great danger thereof, and exhorting all to zeal of the truth. Written by Edward Reynell Esq.</title>
            <author>Reynell, Edward, 1612-1663.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91725</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1216</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E2106_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13720</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859533</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859533</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111621</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91725)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111621)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 241:E2106[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An advice against libertinism shewing the great danger thereof, and exhorting all to zeal of the truth. Written by Edward Reynell Esq.</title>
                  <author>Reynell, Edward, 1612-1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 113, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Abel Roper, at the sun in Fleet-street, over against Saint Dunstons Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Libertinism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111621:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ADVICE Againſt LIBERTINISM; Shewing the great Danger thereof, and exhorting all to Zeal of the TRUTH.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Edward Reynell</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </p>
            <q>Ye have been called unto Liberty, only uſe not Liberty for an occaſion to the fleſh,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 5.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Abel Roper,</hi> at the Sun in Fleet-ſtreet, over againſt Saint <hi>Dunſtons</hi> Church, 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:111621:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111621:2"/>
            <head>AN ADVICE Againſt LIBERTINISM.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not the leaſt of miſeries (in theſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous and licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious <hi>times</hi>) to ſee the thoughts and ſtudies of men taken up for the moſt part in needleſs queſtions (ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely to ſtrife and contention) and not to that <hi>unum neceſſarium,</hi> viz. the knowledge of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the cementing of his ſeamleſs coat,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:111621:3"/>which was never ſo much (and is ſtill more then other) divided, through diſſenting (I might ſay diſtracted) <hi>opinions;</hi> the moſt part alſo bending (like reeds) with every wind of giddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſelf-intereſt; a Religious ſtedfaſtneſs to ſound and fixed prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, being <hi>rara avis</hi> in theſe times of change and backſlid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>And with how much tenderneſs and grief of heart, muſt it needs be reſented, to ſee <hi>Chriſt</hi> perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the name of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> his Word, Ordinances, and Miniſters to be ſo much reviled, and wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the houſe of his ſeeming friends, and that our own ſwords ſhould thus devour our Prophets! <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.30. And truly great reaſon have all thoſe who have found God under a conſtant and painful <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,</hi> to be ſad thereat, ſeeing they thus propheſie in ſack-cloth, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a general unflexibleneſs, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111621:3"/>the great contempt and ſcorn of their <hi>calling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſad principle is taken up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, that we muſt have <hi>liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of <hi>conſcience,</hi> to attend on what <hi>Teachers</hi> or Ordinance we pleaſe, under which, ſome take liberty for their luſts, to attend on <hi>none.</hi> O how ſoon having once (with <hi>Hyme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi>) made ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack of faith, and the means to attain it, ſhall we make ſhipwrack of a good conſcience with it!</p>
            <p>We need not with that famous Orator, <hi>Marcus Antonius,</hi> who to move compaſſion with the people, brought <hi>Caeſars</hi> Robes all bloody a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, much endeavor to manifeſt the truth hereof; and what further may we expect, from ſuch as thus go headlong on, with a preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate opinion, and (reſolving to admit neither debate nor gain-ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) raſhly adventure the precipice of their own <hi>fancy</hi> and endleſs Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mera's,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111621:4"/>ſo often as the tide of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties and giddineſs, ſhall ebb and flow in their unſetled thoughts? ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy alſo being like dead fleſh, which ſoon makes the green wound of an <hi>error</hi> feſter into the ſore of an <hi>Hereſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Never was there ſuch a general defection of <hi>Religion,</hi> as now it ſeems moſt pretended, and held forth; ſuch general <hi>vitiouſneſs,</hi> growth of <hi>Schiſmes,</hi> falſeneſs in <hi>profeſſion;</hi> yea ſuch indifferency therein, without any true warmth, or holy fire of zeal and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>If any new <hi>doctrine</hi> be but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced, the <hi>Author</hi> thereof muſt be thought <hi>Religious;</hi> And ſo backward are we to follow the Sun of Righteouſneſs, as that (if in a dark night) an <hi>Ignis fatuus</hi> do but precede us, or the <hi>miſts</hi> of <hi>error</hi> and ignorance come athwart us; how do their glaring flames amaze
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111621:4"/>our eyes; as if thoſe <hi>falſe lights</hi> were deſign'd on purpoſe to be our pathes; whereas their Rayes lead us onely into into Rivers and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipices!</p>
            <p>And doth not almoſt every hours experience ſhew, how apt we are to embrace their diſcourſes, whoſe doctrine creeps, and corrodes like a Cancer, and hath juſtly driven themſelves from the communion of the Church? who ſteal into the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the ignorant with ſmall, humble, and modeſt beginnings, catch with flattery, binde gently, and at laſt kill privily; their out-ſide of <hi>devotion</hi> (though oftentimes out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhinning a ſincere <hi>Chriſtian</hi>) being but an ill bait to entice us into the nets of <hi>holineſs</hi> and good diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</p>
            <p>Since the more we appear for God, the worſe we are, if we be not that indeed which we appear to be: There is more danger of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111621:5"/>
               <hi>Wolfe</hi> in the <hi>Lambs</hi> skin, then in his own; when once we begin to nauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate at old <hi>Truths,</hi> and (like flies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a candle) to play about <hi>new lights,</hi> its a thouſand to one but we ſinge our wings, if we burn not our ſelves. Thoſe that obſerve the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Eaſtern <hi>Churches;</hi> do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge this as the great provocation of Gods wrath to bring upon them the blaſphemous doctrine of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet,</hi> becauſe they rejected the wholeſom <hi>Truths</hi> of the Goſpel. But what need we go further to prove the ſad experience hereof, then <hi>Germany?</hi> and God grant it appear not amongſt our ſelves, the ſame <hi>flames</hi> of evil <hi>Doctrine</hi> having un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily broken out amongſt us, by thoſe who (as if they had been the ſpaun of thoſe <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles time) account no ſin of power enough to defile them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>by nature ſpiritual.</hi> Some there are,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:111621:5"/>who leading <hi>ſilly women</hi> captive, ſerve their ends upon the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency of the <hi>Sex,</hi> mixing ſcandal with their <hi>hereſie.</hi> Others there are, who having ſurpriſed their will, and poſſeſt their underſtanding with fair <hi>pretences</hi> of their falſe doctrine (our nature being too apte to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what we have a minde to) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently conclude it <hi>Orthodox,</hi> becauſe <hi>ſpreading;</hi> like <hi>icterical</hi> eyes, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the <hi>ſpecies</hi> to the <hi>ſoul</hi> with <hi>colours</hi> of their own making; and we find the moſt pleaſing doctrine to be ever the moſt <hi>taking;</hi> it being the weakneſs of the <hi>Organ,</hi> which thus makes us <hi>blear-eyed,</hi> and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries us headlong into the Precipice of our corrupt <hi>humors;</hi> wherein every man is ſo ſubject to hug his own <hi>opinion,</hi> to hold his hand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Sun</hi> and his face, and yet ſtand ſtaring upon every <hi>meteor,</hi> and inflamed <hi>Comet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:111621:6"/>
And are there not <hi>ſome</hi> who (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their <hi>zeal</hi> kindled at the wrong end, and like nothing ſo well as that which goeth croſs to the grain of <hi>Authority</hi>) when they are looked on, will ſeem to act vertue, with much pompouſneſs, and outward bravery, but when the <hi>Theatre</hi> is empty, will put off their upper gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and retire into their primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive vileneſs? Are there not ſome (ſad <hi>Chriſtians</hi>) benighted in the dark intereſt of coveteouſneſs, and <hi>ambition,</hi> which too often heighren and ſerue up an external <hi>zeal,</hi> by the wooden pins of worldly eſpects, and make no more account of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> then the profit or convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy it brings with it?</p>
            <p>Thus any thing ſeems lawful enough to ſome men, that ſerves the <hi>ends</hi> of their <hi>ambition;</hi> who yet are ſcrupulous enough in caſes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, when nothing of <hi>intereſt</hi> doth intervene; ſo ſadly do evil men
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111621:6"/>in theſe dayes, make <hi>Religion</hi> the ſervant of intereſt; their <hi>deſigns</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therefore the <hi>fouler,</hi> by how much the more they need to put on a <hi>fair</hi> out-ſide.</p>
            <p>But herein (it being bad ſinning in a <hi>Religious</hi> habit) we ought not to frame our <hi>devotions</hi> to their <hi>pattern,</hi> how ſpecious ſo ever they may ſeem to be, according to the model of their own <hi>fancies;</hi> theſe being but the colours of <hi>Religion,</hi> with which the world is too often deceived, by thoſe who cover their <hi>Religion</hi> with a remote <hi>deſign,</hi> leaſt it ſhould appear unhandſome in its own <hi>dreſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our underſtandings being once clouded with bodily pleaſures thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en and become wholly unable for things <hi>divine.</hi> And we may reſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, that thoſe whoſe <hi>deſigns</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretext of <hi>Religion,</hi> ſeek no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the advancement of their Temporal <hi>affairs,</hi> and whoſe good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111621:7"/>humane <hi>Policy</hi> (admitting <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> according to the times, and their own <hi>fancies</hi>) makes uſe of God as a mask for their wickedneſs, will at laſt prove no other then a ſtroke of <hi>Thunder,</hi> which leaves nothing on earth behind it but noiſe and ſtench.</p>
            <p>Were it not madneſs then to paſs through a garden of fair <hi>flowers,</hi> and to take their <hi>poyſon,</hi> and leave their <hi>honey?</hi> Surely <hi>Manna</hi> it ſelf turns into worms, and the wine of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels into vinegar and lees, when it is received into impure <hi>veſſels;</hi> health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful medicines (if abuſed) by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capacities of a healthleſs body, often increaſe the diſtemperature, from indiſpoſition, to a ſharpe diſeaſe; and ſhall we then call that the ſpirit of propheſying, which is the ſpirit of lying; and thoſe things to be <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations,</hi> which are nothing but meer <hi>dreams,</hi> and the fond produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of <hi>Hypocondriacal devotion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:111621:7"/>
Yea how many abſurd <hi>fancies</hi> coming in the likeneſs of <hi>viſions,</hi> and under pretence of <hi>raptures</hi> do we meet with, even from thoſe (the Sun it ſelf producing <hi>ſerpents</hi> when it reflects on the mud of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi>) who ſeem to have been long ſoftned under the continual drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings of the word? though at laſt, all ends in pride or ſome dangerous remptation; ſelf-conceit having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo been not the leaſt <hi>riſe</hi> of ſuch fond and unheard of productions. It being a ſure rule, that whatſoever heights of <hi>piety</hi> any one pretends to, it proceeds from the devil, unleſs the greater the pretence be, the greater be the humility of the man, it being no Paradox to him that ſaid, <hi>Satan had more a do to win the ſimple then the ſubtile;</hi> the worldly wiſe being ſooner enraged then won by the Miniſtry of the word, which croſſes the contentments of the world; neither is pride the leaſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111621:8"/>ſtratagem of hell, to keep the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from profitableneſs under the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of the word, though one of the mighty methods of Satan, to perſwade them to charge the cauſe anywhere, then (where they ought) on their own heart.</p>
            <p>And may we not have juſt cauſe, to queſtion and ſuſpect the variety of thoſe diſpenſations, groundleſly (through too much confidence ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated by diſtempered <hi>fancies</hi>) ſince ſhaking off thoſe excellent patterns of truth and ſincerity in <hi>Religion,</hi> and deviating from thoſe paths which God hath graciouſly chalkt out unto us in his Word and <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> for his Saints to walk in, there being no other courſe (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they mean by Gods revealing himſelf) I mean not what he can extraordinarily do, but in his uſual way) then by thoſe ſaving <hi>Truths,</hi> ſo much now oppos'd, and under re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, and the diſpenſers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:111621:8"/>accounted a burthen fit to be ejected.</p>
            <p>Surely a conſtant Travellers pace over-takes, and out-goes many vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent men, whoſe hot and ill-groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded zeal, is quickly tired; theſe times affording too many ignorant. <hi>Artiſts,</hi> whoſe <hi>zeal</hi> hath been too blind to go right, yet too active to ſtand ſtill; and however the wrinkles of their ſpreading <hi>errors,</hi> were far better confeſt then painted, had much rather ſhelter themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the branible of <hi>diviſon,</hi> then the Olive of <hi>peace,</hi> whoſe ſwarthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs we need not light a candle to diſcover. Thoſe that forſake the good <hi>old way,</hi> to walk in the paths of their own crooked <hi>farcies,</hi> ſeldom meet (at leaſtwiſe with good) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. And may not God leave ſuch as claſh with his Word and <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances,</hi> to looſe themſelves in the dark corners of their own <hi>dolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions;</hi> yea take from them the true
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111621:9"/>
               <hi>light,</hi> they thruſt from themſelves, in forſaking the fountain of <hi>living waters,</hi> and hewing out broken ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterns to themſelves? may he not ſuffer thoſe who ſcorn to ſtrike the ſails of their own wills and intereſt to his ſacred <hi>truth,</hi> and refuſe to eat of the plain food of his word, to be choaked with the bones of their own <hi>inventions?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And oh with what eye of patience can we behold the verities and max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ims of God, which the Prophets foretold us, the Apoſtles denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, the Confeſſors profeſſed, and ſo many thouſands of <hi>Martyrs</hi> have maintained, in the midſt of their flames, their racks, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to be now adayes made the ſport of <hi>giddy ſpirits,</hi> and the aim, and reproach of profane Lips, who void of wit or ſhame thus invade <hi>holy things!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely if our opinion ſo often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us, as that we diſcern little or
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111621:9"/>nothing a right; if all the perfections of this life have ſome imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons mixed with them, yea no knowledge of ours is void of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ignorance (the humble a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſement of our ſelves, being one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſecureſt way to heaven) how ought we to beware of thoſe, who thus brave it in the ſhops, when there is little in the ware-houſe, holding out gaudy fairings, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to colour inward falſities, and ſuborn the truth; the Sun whereof being once ſet in our land, an irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverable midnight of ſpiritual darkneſs, muſt needs ſucceed? If we looſe our eſtates, we may recover them; if we looſe our friends, God can raiſe us up others; if we looſe our lives, we may exchange them for a better; but if we once make ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack of the faith, we are loſt for ever</p>
            <p>And may it not be fear'd that the diſtempered <hi>fancies,</hi> and the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitate headlong <hi>diſcourſes,</hi> now on
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111621:10"/>foot (to the infamous reproach of this age, being ſo full of <hi>errors</hi> and factious ſpirits, inſtead of ſound and Orthodox <hi>truths,</hi> as might much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have invited ſilence then our late contentions) and the too much mingling of humane intereſts with Religion (all being but like the Winters Sun, which ſhines clear, but warms not) will at laſt rend the ſeamleſs coat of the <hi>Church,</hi> and deface the Image which Chriſt hath ſtamped upon it; making <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion another thing then what he deſign'd it to be; when it is ſo far from making us live good lives, that it ſelf is made a pretence to all manner of impiety, and a ſtratagem to ſerve the ends of covetouſneſs, ambition, and revenge.</p>
            <p>And O how great is the vanity of thoſe, who have thus forſaken <hi>God,</hi> to ſerve their own <hi>ends!</hi> and the more, ſeeing they pretend to be <hi>Saints,</hi> before they have put off the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:111621:10"/>
               <hi>ſinner,</hi> and (with <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> and the Phariſees) appear the fouler for being cleanſed. Too often is the crime aggravated by the incivili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the circumſtance; and (as <hi>Abafuerus</hi> ſaid of <hi>Haman, Will he raviſh the Queen in my own houſe?</hi>) the place of Gods worſhip, made the receptacle of buyers and ſellers, there being not a few now a dayes, who thus kiſs a danger, under a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of vertue, and for their own advantage, hug an opportunity of <hi>ſin</hi> under pretence of <hi>piety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, how ſad it is to ſee thoſe who pretend themſelves to be the onely friends of the Church, ſo violently to affect the rich and pompous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venews, and Prelacies, which they ſeem eagerly to oppoſe, and not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (like thoſe Eccleſiaſticks in Saint <hi>Bernards</hi> time, who purſued their own preferment, not the peoples welfare, and (like uſurping Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors) grow revengfully jealous,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:111621:11"/>through covetuouſneſs, polluting themſelves with the puddles of this world, but (like thoſe vipers who eat out the womb of their Mother) bring beaſts into the Temple, and as well expoſe the Temple it ſelf to ſale, as make the holy Rites thereunto belonging, venal, and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive.</p>
            <p>God indeed (who loves thoſe deereſt whom he corrects) may for a time ſuffer his ſword to be abuſed, and the wicked to cover their perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious deſigns, under the cloak of Religion and the mask of hypocriſie. But ſurely, ſuch as make but a Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Robe of <hi>Religion,</hi> and take the liberty to embrace that which beſt becomes their occaſions, will at laſt appear (however they take upon them to ſit in the chair of Divinity, and how great a noiſe ſoever they make, as the ſons of thunder) not to have been educated in the Schools of the Prophets.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:111621:11"/>
Its vain for him to ſeek to fence himſelf without, whoſe foe is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him; or to make the pretence of piety the pander to his own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſs. Its well known, that the mind too often covers paſſion under a cloak of ſeveral colours. The weeping of an <hi>heir,</hi> is but laughing under a diſguiſe; and the greateſt number of our actions but veil'd over with diſſimulation, which an all-ſeeing providence will at laſt, no doubt, as well diſcover, as puniſh; ſince he that thus leaps from Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to hypocriſie, and thereby of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends others to defend himſelf, ſerves not God, but makes God ſerve his own turn; neither is ſacriledge, which hath of late found ſo fine a dreſs, and ſeems to bear the greateſt ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor amongſt many ſinns, the way to keep our purpoſes from canker, or our ſtomacks from windineſs; ſince it uſually makes a fair eſtate to evaporate, and turn to nothing; no
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111621:12"/>one knows which way; onely expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience tells us, that vice often times gets money and a curſe withall; it being alſo Gods intent to teach us, that as the good have ſomething elſe to hope for, ſo the wicked ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what elſe to fear, then the good or bad fortune of this world.</p>
            <p>It is not denied, but that ſome who have been fatted up with the Altar, have many times been ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Altar: But what? If ſome one abuſe Myſteries, muſt we over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw Churches? Muſt Ordinances, Miniſters, Maintenance, and all be eradicated? What if ſome evil <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> grow ſuperſtitious, muſt we fall into the other <hi>extream</hi> of <hi>Liberti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm?</hi> Muſt innocency be forſaken for the guilties ſake? If ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars introduce exorbitant devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, let them be blamed, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and rejected, none will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to defend or juſtifie them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:111621:12"/>
But ſurely as they are bad clouds which thus obſcure the Sun which raiſed them, and have as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith [if ever] begotten them to the faith, ſo are they ſpirits of a very poor inferior order, that thus quit their ſtation upon diſcontents, being but the Apes of thoſe melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Schiſmaticks, who (having burnt off their own Fingers, in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the world on fire) are now faln out with it becauſe they cannot rule it.</p>
            <p>And truly, great care muſt be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, leaſt we proſtitute our ſouls to theſe falſe Gods of ſtraw and dung, and for a tuneable cadence of a few ſmooth words, we loſe all the harmonies of faith and a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; ſince from the opinion of their own abilities, they cry down the houſes of Gods worſhip, and the maintenance thereof, the better to make way to their own purpoſes, yea take upon them to cenſure all
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:111621:13"/>
               <hi>Ecclefiaſtical</hi> Perſons as needleſſe, if not <hi>Antichriſtian;</hi> not ſeeing that the contempt of <hi>Religion</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes began by the contempt of the <hi>Miniſtry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is to be feared, that ſome who of late have built their own houſes at the expence of Gods houſe, will in time find the Rafters and Beams of ſuch <hi>Edifices,</hi> to ſerve as inſtruments of puniſhment to thoſe that have raiſed them; loth I am (I confeſs) to judge unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably of thoſe, who in ſeeming thus to avoid <hi>ſuperſtition,</hi> have created <hi>devotions</hi> to themſelves, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline thereunto; yet much fear that ſuch, as by this way think to touch heaven with their finger, have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready one foot in the vale of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>Neither would I willingly ſoyl the purity of my pen with the exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitancies of thoſe, who neglecting pious preſidents, and the eſſential
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:111621:13"/>
               <hi>maxims</hi> of faith, adhere to the ſilly inventions of their own ſpirit, and as ſpeedily run into thoſe follies which haſten unto the heigth of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolency and deſtruction.</p>
            <p>For, Great God! what a ſtroak of Thunder is this to reformed <hi>Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches?</hi> what aſtoniſhment in all or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, what a wound in the heart of <hi>Religion,</hi> to ſee thy <hi>Laborers</hi> caſt out of thy <hi>vine-yard,</hi> their mainten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance queſtioned [or at leaſt repin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly afforded] and the places of thy worſhip wholly extirpated? Alas! that ever men ſhould ſo carry on their own intereſts, with ſuch vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of paſſion, to the heigth of their pretentions, as to hold Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the beauty thereof in ſo great contempt, without the leaſt ſeeming touch of ſorrow or repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance!</p>
            <p>And no leſs reaſon have they who have of late rent the <hi>Church</hi> into ſo many <hi>Schiſmes,</hi> by fraught<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111621:14"/>its ſhip (like that of <hi>Jonah</hi>) with a miſcelany of all Nations, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it to contain, as many <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> as once <hi>Babel</hi> did <hi>languages,</hi> to cry out with <hi>Nero</hi> (that lively Image of cruelty) when he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to ſign the death of a crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, offender; O would to God I could never have written! And oh that I could ſay unto thoſe as once <hi>Peter</hi> did to the people, <hi>I wot that through ignorance ye did it, as did alſo your Rulers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alas, how ſoon have ſome for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten their firſt love towards the <hi>Embaſſadors</hi> of God, by whom [if ever] they were begotten in the Lord! If any thing go amiſs with the people, <hi>Aaron</hi> muſt be ſtoned. How ſadly doth <hi>Iſmael's,</hi> as well as <hi>Eſau's</hi> perſecution (<hi>oris &amp; plagae,</hi> that of the tongue as well as the hand) appear amongſt them! The devil ſeem'd ſomething merciful to our Saviour, he would not have him
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:111621:14"/>ſtarve but to turn ſtones into bread, while ſome of late, leſſe charitable, would have the faithful and Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Church of God to live upon ſtones, inſtead of bread; but it is no wonder that they who once made the <hi>Lords day</hi> a delight unto them, and ſaw beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the feet of thoſe who brought the glad tidings of peace, and flock't like Doves to the holes of the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows (having ſince queſtioned whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be the Lords Ordinance, or mans, and endeavour'd as much as in them lay, to make the ways of <hi>Sion</hi> to mourn, and to ſtop the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers thereof) ſhould account their <hi>Miniſters</hi> a charge and burthen in their places.</p>
            <p>However let not thoſe of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>calling,</hi> be troubled who ſtand idle in the Market place, becauſe no man hath hired them, ſeeing their ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings can no way be counted their fault, it being as dangerous a perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:111621:15"/>of <hi>Religion</hi> to with-draw the fewel from it, as to caſt water on it. And how much were it to be wiſh't that the two-edged ſword of thoſe who give out, as if heaven and not they, had intended the partition, did not cut more for their own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment and advantage, than for Gods glory, though like greedy gameſters (having all in their hand) they loſe all at laſt, by ſtealing a needleſs card, it being no eaſie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to reduce <hi>divine things</hi> to our own ballance, ſo as they ſuffer no impeachment.</p>
            <p>Religion and Sacrifice had their beginning from the worlds infancy, and have by an indiviſible tye, been evermore linked together. God who giveth all to us, will have us give all to him, though eſpecially he require our actions, our affections, &amp; our ſelves in the duties of his ſervice. And ſure where we cannot give the whole Tree, with ſuch perfection, as
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:111621:15"/>we would, yet at leaſt let us argue our willingneſs by giving part of the fruit to his glory.</p>
            <p>But how ſoon will thoſe, who have once loſt their underſtanding and conſcience, find a beaten path to infidelity! How ſoon will they cut and mangle things relating to the furtherance and honor of Gods truths, and the Oeconomy of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion! It having been an old maxime (if not dotage) amongſt obſequious ſpirits (having no zeal for faith, nor courage againſt impiety) to approve all <hi>Religions,</hi> and follow none. And certainly, he that ſhall go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to define this falſe <hi>liborty</hi> of belief, and manners now adayes crept in among us, ſhall find it no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but a meer dependance on fancy and paſſion: It is (ſaith one) a ſtrange <hi>Monſter,</hi> whereof it ſeems <hi>Job</hi> (<hi>Job</hi> 40.) made diſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, under the figure of <hi>Behemoth.</hi> For as this creature ſeems compoſed
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111621:16"/>of all ſorts of <hi>beaſts,</hi> ſo is <hi>Libertin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme</hi> a ſin framed out of all maner of <hi>ſins,</hi> to annihilate the moſt ſincere part of <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi> It draws a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with it, a great train of vices, and corruptions, which tend di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to the utter deſolation of <hi>Kingdoms</hi> and <hi>Empires.</hi> And as for thoſe hideous puniſhments obſerved in all Ages to have befaln thoſe Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Provinces, and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, which have bred, or favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, ſuch as have run over the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of Antiquity, ſhall find expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riences enough.</p>
            <p>Neither can we poſſibly believe that <hi>devotion</hi> to be good, which is ſo extreamly ſubject to <hi>novelties,</hi> ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities, and pride, which proceeds from a fooliſh confidence of our own judgement. It being well known to all, that the moſt fatal plague in Religion, and devotion, is the deſire to ſeek direction from our own ſtrength, and opinion; men
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:111621:16"/>that are eaſily enflamed in matters of Religion, fail not as ſpeedily to raiſe ſedition. Moſt ſtrange! that we ſhould thus miſerably loſe our ſelves in the <hi>ignis fatuus</hi> of our own <hi>fancies,</hi> and that (though we cannor reform a ſilly flie in the work of nature) we will yet frame a new work of <hi>Religion,</hi> which derives its accompliſhment onely from God.</p>
            <p>And what is this but to make a <hi>Roman Pantheon</hi> of Religion, where there are a thouſand <hi>Divinities,</hi> without the leaſt glimmer, or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the true God? And is it not a pitiful thing to ſee ſome in our times, profeſſing Religion, to take the ſame <hi>liberty</hi> to themſelves? or is it not a thing moſt unhanſome, to ſee an infamous fellow, to make himſelf the cenſurer of <hi>Divinity,</hi> and corrector of the Scripture? doth it become them to talk of the Bible, and the holy <hi>Myſteries</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:111621:17"/>[too ſadly oftentimes wreſted by that blaſphemous breath, which holds forth nothing ſo much as ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, ſcoffing, and ſycophancy, from which we ought to ſhut our <hi>ears,</hi> if we cannot ſtop their <hi>mouthes?</hi>]</p>
            <p>It is obſerved of the <hi>Bat,</hi> that he imployes the Chriſtalline humor of his eyes to enlarge his wings, though very uſeleſs, and to no purpoſe; ſo how many are there now a dayes, who conſume the <hi>light</hi> they have received from God to create wings of pride, novelty, and vanity, which ſerve them to flie in the night of ignorance?</p>
            <p>And O the ſad opinions of our <hi>Times!</hi> which (wandring from the <hi>Rayes</hi> of wholeſome <hi>Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine</hi>) prove but the <hi>Chymeraes</hi> of piety, Spectres of madneſſe, and flames which lead poore ſoules into the <hi>Abyſſe</hi> of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe! What alas! may we (with
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:111621:17"/>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Doctrinae pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rientibus auri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus natae. Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tul. de Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi>) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude ſuch illuſions, and <hi>Phantaſmes,</hi> but as the doctrines of Satan, grown up to pleaſe the itch of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulous ears? ſince they more tend to dazel our <hi>ſight,</hi> than to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our <hi>judgement,</hi> or inflame our deſires.</p>
            <p>There are many things (I confeſs) unknown, wherein God will exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe our faith, but not ſatisfie our curioſity, and we ſtill ought to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor a clearer diſcovery of his will. Nothing in all <hi>Ages</hi> hath been ſo hidden as <hi>Truth.</hi> The Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers (thoſe great <hi>lamps</hi> of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) contended much in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſection and defence thereof, but much diſmembred it in the ill hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thereof, leaving it in cloudy Caverns, all covered with ſhades and darkneſs, and in ſtead of a ſolid body retained nought in their hands
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:111621:18"/>but a <hi>Phantaſme.</hi> But though blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man, infected with the immortal diſeaſe of incredulity, hath Giant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like perſecuted it through contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and vanity of ſpirit, God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone through his infinite goodneſs, hath been the diſcoverer there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            <p>And ſure it were but fondneſſe to think, that in the declining Age of the world, the way to heaven were yet to ſeek, ſince the eternal wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom hath taken lips of fleſh to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal the ſecrets thereof unto us; how furiouſly ſoever his divine <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> have been aſſaulted on all hands, by Jews, Gentiles, Mahumetans, Hereticks, to which we may adde the <hi>Libertines</hi> of our <hi>Times,</hi> of whom we may juſtly doubt, leaſt their ſecure ambition prove no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then <hi>Archimedes</hi> his Engine, whereon the higher any mounted, the lower they deſcended.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:111621:18"/>
Yea good reaſon have we to doubt (ſince they that will never fall, muſt ever fear) leaſt that pride, which perpetually exalts them, will (through giddineſſe) at laſt, precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate them into the Abyſſe of thoſe <hi>fantaſies,</hi> which they have meerly borrowed from their ſhallow inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and which they too often en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title (through the ſottiſh apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of then mind) with the name of <hi>viſions</hi> and <hi>revelations,</hi> which may be refuted with as much eaſe as they are invented, ſeeing that they carry with them but the bare and feeble pretext of <hi>Religion,</hi> neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the effects.</p>
            <p>Neither is it credible that <hi>Truth</hi> ſhould be ſo long hidden, to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered to ſuch kind of men as ſeek to ſow ſuch dangerous <hi>maxims</hi> in our mind; creatures of little Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, evil manners, of a conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation inſolent, or covert, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that ſanctity, miracles, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111621:19"/>they ſo much plead for. And ſurely, we ſtand not in need of ſuch kind of curioſity, to ſeek after <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> of to ſearch for the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel. The Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly telling us, That <hi>if an Angel from heaven ſhould preach any other unto us, we ought to change nothing of our belief,</hi> which ſo many millions of <hi>Martyrs</hi> have ſealed with their blood; which the beſt part of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind hath profeſſed, and the wiſeſt heads of the world illuſtrated in their writings.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Faith</hi> is not grounded upon wit, diſcourſe, or natural judgement, but on the ſubmiſſion and duty we owe to the Truths and Ordinances of God; from which, whoſoever wandereth ſhall finde nothing but an <hi>Ocean</hi> of diſturbances, and the ſhipwrack of his <hi>Faith,</hi> which he ought not to abandon to a Caitive ſpirit, which hath nothing ſpecious in it but illuſion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:111621:19"/>
There is but one Redeemer, to whom we all owe our ſervices and adorations. <hi>Jeſus</hi> hath nothing to do with <hi>Belial,</hi> nor the temple of God with the Synagogue of Satan. And however <hi>lyes</hi> may for a time, ſeem to accord together, yet true <hi>Religion</hi> is ever ſound in it ſelf; and to approve any other (though ſeemingly never ſo reaſonable) is but to thruſt thorns into the feet, and ſtraws into the eyes; neither will it ſeem any ſtrange thing, that thoſe who ſeek their contentments, and the pleaſing of their <hi>fancies,</hi> in the contempt of God and his <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances,</hi> ſhould at laſt make up but a bad reckoning, pricking their fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers whilſt they are gathering of <hi>Roſes,</hi> and meeting with worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood in the midſt of <hi>Honey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet (though God be never ſo great as when he appeareth little to humane underſtanding) how ſadly do we find haughtineſs &amp; arrogancy
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111621:20"/>to have puffed up many (through their ſmall ſmattering of gifts) with the opinion of their own capacity? They think themſelves onely to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce oracles, and judge all other men to conſiſt of ſuperſtitions and ideotiſme. The Fathers are enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained like Grooms in their Stables. Points of Logick, profoundneſſe in the Scriptures, reading of Councels, with the knowledge of things natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, are no way thought worthy their better thoughts.</p>
            <p>I deny not, but as that which is given us by the favour of Heaven, comes very readily, and is never loſt; ſo that which comes to us by Art, oftentimes begins very late and quickly ends [the love of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſcience not ſtudied, where the infuſion of his holy ſpirit is more e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquent then all tongues, and more learned then all pens] yet doth it not hence follow, that all humane learning is to be rejected. Though
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:111621:20"/>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> deſired to know nothing but <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> yet did he not contemne all other knowledge and humane learning in Arts and Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, wherein himſelf was ſo accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh't, being the great Doctor of the Gentiles, and could ſpeak tongues more than they all, he onely diſliked it ſo far as it ſtood in oppoſition againſt, or in competition with the knowledge of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And it would be of great moment, to the greateſt intereſt of theſe mens ſouls, if they would but make ſo much uſe of their natural Logick, as to detect thoſe fallacies which are put upon their reaſons, by their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate deſires, either of profit, or pleaſure or worldly ambition.</p>
            <p>Some there are indeed (though the feweſt amongſt them) who ſeem to have arived to ſome perfection in humane Sciences; but alas! How do they vex the world with their tatle! neither will their ſpirit admit any
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:111621:21"/>other path, but Precipices: and if a capable man ſound theſe ſwelling <hi>Rodomantaes,</hi> oh what empty cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers will appear in their brains! what darkneſſe! what confuſion! All their learning is but like guilded gates peſtered with ſpiders, which too uſually ſlights the ſyllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſmes of the Schools, and hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the arguments of tyrants, which are arms and violence.</p>
            <p>But (ſince the life of oppoſites is in comparing them) I do not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that <hi>learning</hi> (as well as the <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors</hi> thereof) are ſuch great rubs in their way; ſeeing their ignorance muſt needs appear thereby to be the more palpable; and their deſire is to enter into the <hi>fold</hi> like <hi>Wolves</hi> in a <hi>Sheeps</hi> skin. They tell the ſheep they are much affected to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, but that the dogs muſt be taken away, which do nothing but deafen their ears with barking.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:111621:21"/>
They would willingly make you believe, the mire of their ignorance to be ſweet, becauſe they delight to tumble in it; or that the Spider or Toad are no poyſon, becauſe ſome things eat them, and miſcarry not, though the beam in their eye is not the leſs becauſe their eye doth not ſee it; nor is their ignorance the leſs, their puniſhment, becauſe they are affected with it. But ſeeing it is thus too often the imperfection of our nature, not to think our lips foul after our putrid and rotten diſcourſe (though they are defiled) as we ought to deſire God to ſet a watch before the door of our own lips, leaſt we ſhould offend with our tongue; ſo ſhould we very cautelous, and with <hi>Vlyſſes,</hi> binde our ſelves to the maſt, and ſtop our ears with wax leaſt we ſhould be deceived with the voice of theſe <hi>Syrens,</hi> not beholding their claws.</p>
            <p>It is reported of <hi>Democritus,</hi> that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:111621:22"/>he voluntarily made himſelf blind, by looking ſtedfaſtly on the beams of the <hi>Sun,</hi> to free himſelf from the importunity of the love of women, who might perchance have ſhut up two gates againſt love, to open a thouſand to his fond imagination. (<hi>Tertul. Apologet.</hi>) And the like we read of <hi>Origen,</hi> that he deprived himſelf of the diſtinction of <hi>Sex,</hi> to rebate the ſtings of ſenſuality, which bred him much miſchief. Surely no leſs reaſon have we not onely to fear the fire, but avoid the ſmoak of thoſe incendiaries, which (like <hi>Sampſons</hi> Foxes) have of late added ſuch flames towards the <hi>diviſions</hi> of Church and State.</p>
            <p>Yea, how neceſſary is it for us to come out from amongſt thoſe creeping Serpents, which ſteal into the hearts of thoſe they deſtroy? and which (like certain rocks hidden under the waves) ſurprize Sailors, and cauſe grievous ſhip-wracks. Ah!
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:111621:22"/>how many have been deceived by their impoſtures? How many ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving once made ſhip-wrack of their <hi>Reaſon,</hi> have thereunto added the ſhip-wrack of their <hi>Faith?</hi> the ſwelling preſumption of their ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary abilities, creating a barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of judgement, diſcretion, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, and conſequently of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian vertues.</p>
            <p>In all which reſpects, they that will but a little obſerve their incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, having no other bounds but their own intereſt, and like wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-cocks, turning their faces which way ſoever the wind blows; he that obſerveth that <hi>pride</hi> which puffeth them up, that <hi>ambition</hi> which precipitateth them, and how often <hi>impudence</hi> makes them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable, ſhall find them peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whoſe humors conſiſt much of of air and water, pliant and ſupple to all manner of Doctrines, and attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with variety of petty <hi>phantaſmes,</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:111621:23"/>imperfect in ſhape, and not a little tranſporting their judgement which too often alſo (through the ſharpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their Paſſions) diſcovers it ſelf either notably weak, or much benumbed; their whole life appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing elſe, but the ebb and flood of a continuall <hi>Euripus,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed with ſhadows, giddineſſe, and illuſions.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not be ſo uncharitable, as ſome have been (who with much more diſcretion might have covered the ſtains of their mother the <hi>Church,</hi> then with ſuch malignity of ſpirit to divulge them) to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute the diſorders of particulars to the general body; it being neither fit, nor reaſonable for the ſake of ſome blaſted <hi>members,</hi> to blame ſound parts, neither for the fickle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſome, to cenſure the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of many more <hi>pious,</hi> whom by duty we are obliged to tender with no leſſe prudence then charineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:111621:23"/>
But I ſhall paſſe them by (as Bees over Hemlock) with advice onely to all ſuch as have thus far taken <hi>Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions</hi> in ſtead of good fiſh, and embraced <hi>Hyaena</hi>'s through miſtake of friends, ſeriouſly to conſider, that as there is nothing more ſincere than <hi>Religion,</hi> and one that liveth in the true Rules and <hi>duties</hi> thereof; ſo when corruption falls thereinto, nothing proves more dangerous and hurtful. And as Domeſtick Armes are much more to be feared than outward Hoſtility; ſo who ſees not, but that being now in the haven, ſurprized with a grievous ſtorm of <hi>Sects,</hi> and <hi>Errors</hi> amongſt our ſelves, it muſt not onely ſnatch from us our comfort, but (like ill managed wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons) turn againſt our own breaſt, to the rending out of our own en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trails; yea, even to the very ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our ſouls! ſince our di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions are ſo much the more dangerous beyond common wars,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:111621:24"/>as the Spirit is above the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</p>
            <p>He that endeavoreth to divide Religion, hath none at all. He that admitteth but one leak, drowns a ſhip, and he that reſolves to believe but a part, and not the whole, believes nothing, ſince all comes from the ſame Authority, and muſt be equally received. There is but one word (ſaith <hi>Tertullian, Tert. de Praeſcript. cont. Haereſ.</hi>) to determine all ſort of diſputations with ſuch men. Do but ask them, whither they will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce their Baptiſme and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity; if ſo, let them wear the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, and go amongſt the heathen. But if they make profeſſion of one ſame <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and one ſame <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> why do they belye their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion?</p>
            <p>But ſurely <hi>Art</hi> will not, it is onely <hi>Grace,</hi> and the gift of God, which can charm ſuch <hi>Baſilisks,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing creatures amongſt all others,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:111621:24"/>hard to be enchanted. It is only a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine light and guidance, which muſt direct thoſe who thus loſe their <hi>faith</hi> in their <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and bury their <hi>heaert</hi> in their <hi>brains,</hi> who have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to their own <hi>fancies,</hi> more than to the divine <hi>oracles</hi> of that written word inſpired from heaven, who think the <hi>Miniſters</hi> thereof <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian,</hi> or at leaſt wiſe (ſince dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering with them) to be too ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laced in their opinions, and making the way to heaven narrower than God ever meant it; who (to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent amongſt men) leave the beaten tract, neglecting the good old way, and to guide their ſteps by the dim <hi>lanthorns</hi> (as they call them) of the Antient, tread in the <hi>new paths</hi> of their own <hi>inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> who think to pretend Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is to do any thing; to ſeem ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is to be what we will, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no face ſo foul, which that mask cannot cleanly colour; who, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:111621:25"/>they think themſelves more holy, more wiſe, better gifted, more enlightened than their neighbors, think they may juſtly over-look them with contempt and cenſure, and not onely in publike meetings, bur in ordinary converſation, avoid the contagion of ſuch common breath. And however the <hi>zeal</hi> of ſome ſcrupulous Preachers (as they ſay) is pleas'd to make the worſt of their ſlips, yet have they certain fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable circumſtances, if not who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to excuſe them, yet ſufficiently to rebate the edge of divine ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>Let us take then the ballance in our hand, and judge if it be not worſe then a barbarous ingratitude, thus to worſhip our own fancies; to ſteal the ſilver and gold of <hi>God,</hi> and make idols to <hi>Baal;</hi> to light our lamp at his Altar, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to make pillage of his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which aſſuredly they do, when
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:111621:25"/>they not onely pride themſelves in their ſhame, but abuſe all the gifts of heaven in ambitious impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
            <p>It was good advice which one gave to a ſoul deſirous of advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; namely, to remember three things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To addict it ſelf much to the preſence of God.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond,</hi> To take the holy Scripture for the rule of our acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>third,</hi> to hold firm foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in conſtancy.</p>
            <p>Would thoſe who pretend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the moſt refined ſpirits of the <hi>times</hi> (whoſe mouths and hearts notwithſtanding reſemble <hi>Cyclope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>s</hi> Caverns, rather then the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Peace and <hi>Truth</hi>) would thoſe (I ſay) who make the ſmooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) of their tongue an Engine to credit their deſigns, and with <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolom</hi> cover their Rebellion with a
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:111621:26"/>fit of devotion to pay their vows, but ſeriouſly conſider thoſe few ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſements, they would not ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten perſonate the <hi>Saint</hi> to play the <hi>devil;</hi> neither make their good <hi>words</hi> ſo often to become their <hi>ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Would they who (being no way waſhed from their own leproſie) puddle the ſacred ſprings of whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome doctrine, and like <hi>Sorcerers,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor to caſt miſts on the faireſt morning, but bethink themſelves, if <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> for putting falſe fire into their Incenſories when they came to the Altar of the Synagogue, were devoured as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Victims, with the proper coals of their own Sacrifice; what will become of them who adore Chriſt to cruciſie him in his <hi>Truths,</hi> and who thus irreverently preſume to approach the Altar of the eternal Teſtament? will not their ſacrifice prove their puniſhment, ſince they
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:111621:26"/>have made a ſin of their propitiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? And as proſperous victories ill diſciplined, bring with them more damage then defeatments do; will not thoſe divine <hi>Myſteries</hi> (which were formerly beheld clouded in darkneſs, but are now more appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently obſerved in a clear sky) occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion their greater ruine, who under ſo glorious a Sun-ſhine thus turn <hi>prety</hi> into ſcoffs, and retain nothing of it but a <hi>Phantaſme,</hi> to ſerve their own ends, and to lacquay in their vile affections?</p>
            <p>Would thoſe who ſeem to breath nothing but <hi>Stoiciſme</hi> and ſpiritual-mindedneſs, who bear a vicious mind in a fair ornament of body, and cover a leaden weapon in an Ivory ſheath, but ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that to be godly is to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and to be pious is to be juſt (godlineſs and honeſty, being divine in conjunction, but (divided from one another) are moſt abominable
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:111621:27"/>things) would they I ſay with their <hi>Janus</hi> faces, think they can worſhip <hi>God,</hi> ſo long as they hate, and prove falſe to their <hi>neighbor,</hi> whom they may plunder in love, and perſecute their body to ſave their ſouls? Who obſerves not that thoſe men who thus ſtray from the Rules of heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſdom, precipitate themſelves into devious enormitie, and caligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous obſervations? ſuch ſpirits being willing to be found anywhere than where they may obſerve Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>duties.</hi> Devotion, Temperance, Chriſtian Charity, and other vertues, are not now accounted of in the ſouls of ſuch diſſolute <hi>Liberties;</hi> as if the bare reputation of being devout, might draw upon it ſome ſuſpition of weakneſſe: yea, how many now adays are troubled, that nature hath not made them impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent enough to ſhake off the ſting of a good conſcience, as if hell were no other then in picture with them?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:111621:27"/>
Nor could it otherwiſe be that ſo many uncollected ſpirits now a days [as if they would frame the whole work of Religion to their own hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor] ſhould make it their gloty to act all againſt the hair, to oppoſe the moſt ſound opinions, and to give the lye even to heaven it ſelf; yea as if they were ſo many <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medes,</hi> who ſeek for a place out of the world to ſet foot in, of purpoſe to turn the world topſie turvey; it would not be that ſo many hideous monſters of hereſies, of impiety and Atheiſm, ſhould ſo uncontrol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably throw forth Blaſphemies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Religion,</p>
            <p>And doth not Religion, and the glory of God herein ſuffer diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? doth not our Nation labor under general convulſions? Hath it not been waſted through unheard of lacerations? Is it not (I ſay) through the terrible and monſtruous ſpreadings of <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> and ſelf-will'd
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:111621:28"/>
               <hi>opinions</hi> under which the <hi>Church</hi> of God now laboreth, and the oppreſſive ſighs of a mourning people are almooſt tired out with te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious diſappointments?</p>
            <p>Surely, he that ſees the Church of God [once glorious, and trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing] to be now ſo full of rubbiſh and deſormity; he that ſees her now complaining, bedew'd with tears, ſitting in the duſt, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt drown'd in cares and ſorrows, muſt needs cry out with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet (<hi>Lam.</hi> 1.1.) <hi>How doth the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſit ſolitary, that was full of people! how is ſhe becom as a widdow! ſhe that was great among the Nations, and Princeſs among the Provinces, how is ſhe become tributary?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All that is juſt, prudent, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate, now taſteth too much of common; other paths muſt be found to heaven, new ways muſt be cut out from God under the mould of our own Fancy, to make him known un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:111621:28"/>us; every one thinking that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion moſt probable which he hath taken upon byaſſe of his own under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
            <p>And hence is it that ſo often we court a <hi>fancy</hi> or body of ſmoak, thinking to entertain a <hi>Truth</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving much of affectation, but leaſt of effect, ſince we tie our ſelves to a rotten <hi>branch,</hi> in ſtead of adhering to the body of the <hi>Tree.</hi> Hence is it that we ſee ſo many in the ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of affected Piety, who ſo well act all countenances, as if with ſuch merchandize Paradiſe were to be purchaſed, being yet in heart like thoſe pearls which in ſtead of a ſolid body have nothing but the husk.</p>
            <p>And is it not from this that ſo many take devotion as a ſlight pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime? others but as a ſlight com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, that ſome bend that way for complacency of humors; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for vain-glory, yea, too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are thereto tranſported for ſome
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:111621:29"/>ſlender cloak of liberty, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain accommodations of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per intereſt, expreſſing an unſeemly devotion of Apiſh tricks, which conſiſt in a certain light, and childiſh imitation of countenances and geſtures without any ſolidity in the interior?</p>
            <p>Oprodigy! now adays to ſee ſo many, who are only bold to do ill, but in undertakings made for God and his truth, have hearts of wax, and ſouls trembling like leaves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the breath of windes! As there is almoſt nothing ſo pittiful as a Prince diſarmed (who ſerves onely as a But to reproaches, and a ſport to inſolency) ſo what Rock would not be mollified among ſo many direful objects? what eye office would not melt among ſo many ſpectacles of ſadneſs, to behold God diſroabed of his Honor, his Truths, his Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, by thoſe who being drowned in the inundation of impleties, follow
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:111621:29"/>him by a muddy ſearch, rather then by a clear acquiſt?</p>
            <p>Is not this to betray <hi>Religion,</hi> which of it ſelf, is fair and glorious? And do we not hereby give occaſion to exorbitant ſouls, to juſtifie their <hi>ſins</hi> by our evil deportments, who think that by depainting vice with a coal in another, they make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as white as ſnow? what need we thus go about to entertain ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded fantaſies? and as ſorcereſſes darken the glorious eye of the day with their charms to cloud our faith by renouncing the light of truth, by embracing the dusky vapors of our own inventions?</p>
            <p>Are not the <hi>Truths</hi> of God hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto held forth unto us ſufficient? Why then [by <hi>diſentombing</hi> thoſe <hi>Hereſies,</hi> which were long ſince en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred] do we draw on us the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of <hi>Infidels,</hi> which will at laſt ſerve us to no other purpoſe but to reproach us in the eternity of our
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:111621:30"/>pains with the exorbitance of our infamy!</p>
            <p>They who adulterate metals, and poiſon the <hi>ſources</hi> of lively <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains,</hi> do leſs hurt then thoſe who uſe their own intereſt for <hi>Text,</hi> their ignorance for gloſſe, and their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for commentary. Neither do thoſe who deſire to eſtabliſh falſe things, gain ought elſe upon the credulity of humane ſpirits, but to make <hi>Truth</hi> to be the more doubted. For as ill habites are eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made to ſlide into the hearts of children, by imitation of parents, or corruption of evil company; ſo error illaqueates ſome men, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion ſets the complexion upon the procedures of the moſt.</p>
            <p>And what is this but to oppoſe the ſhadow to the light, and a lye to the truth? Nay, do we not herein ſet up <hi>Reaſon</hi> as Judge, and reſolve our <hi>Faith</hi> into <hi>Reaſon?</hi> [an error of too many in theſe dayes.] Do we
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:111621:30"/>not give vice the colour of vertue, and keep truth in Iron chains? yea, which is worſe, imitate the ſorcerers who imploy the Bible to fortifie their enchantments?</p>
            <p>Experience hath of late too ſadly told us, that there is nothing which ſo much tempts Curioſity, as Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from whence it comes, that (as <hi>Jonah's</hi> ſhip) every one ſeems to call upon his own God; that the figure ſo much encroacheth upon the body, and that (like men ſmitten with blindneſſe) we are led into <hi>Samaria,</hi> in ſtead of going to <hi>Dothan,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 6.19.</p>
            <p>But where we ſee any thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to have new inſtincts towards diſcoveries, above and beyond Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, let us with the Apoſtle (<hi>Col.</hi> 2.18, 19.) make it a marke of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers, to intrude into things they have not ſeen; and however in the eſteem of ſome they are as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent as Apoſtles, or an Angel
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:111621:31"/>of God, yet if they once throw aſide this glaſs, introducing new and ſtrange Doctrines (though under great humility and ſhews of love) if they go about to cauſe <hi>diviſions,</hi> if they forſake Ordinances, vilifie Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and the old way of holy walking with God, we are bound not to receive, but to avoid them, leaſt we be deceived (as <hi>Adam</hi> was) and loſe that knowledge of God which once we had.</p>
            <p>Alas! why ſhould we thus betray the glory of God? why do we thus batter his inheritance? Are not our continued <hi>diviſions</hi> the cauſe that <hi>the wayes to Sion do mourn, that her Prieſts ſigh, and ſhe is afflicted, that all her beauty is departed? her princes are become like Harts that finde no paſture, and are gone without ſtrength before the purſuer,</hi> Lament. 1.4.6. Have not our breaches been the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rode of ſo many licentious enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities? Is it not from the fruitful
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:111621:31"/>mother of diſſentions, that ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny impieties and the Authors there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of have increaſt amongſt us, and though not acted by command, yet tolerated by connivance?</p>
            <p>What is it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he that hath ſo much diſobliged the deſires, and fruſtrated the expectations of all men? How comes it that their minds are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, and their vertues diſheart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? whence comes it that the <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> is ſo vilipended, the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> contemn'd, and all things ſeem perverted? was it not by the too furious marchings of thoſe <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hu's,</hi> who at firſt made way to their ambitious expectations by all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns [either violent or fradulent] and whoſe beſt <hi>luſtures</hi> have ſince proved but a <hi>foil</hi> to Religion, that <hi>piety</hi> languiſheth, <hi>Religion</hi> fainteth, that <hi>charity</hi> is accounted ſcandalous and <hi>ſuperſtitious;</hi> that blaſphemy aſſumes the uncontroled liberty of venting, and that the beauty of <hi>Churches</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:111621:32"/>is ſo diſgraced and ſullied by ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious hands?</p>
            <q>Faelices nimium bona ſi ſua norint!</q>
            <p>How happy had we been, had we learn't rather to <hi>live</hi> than to <hi>diſpute?</hi> had the waters of ſtrife, and the floods of contention been dried up, how ſoon had that <hi>Dove</hi> with ſilver wings appeared amongſt us? Had that charity which is onely infuſed into us by the ſpirit of God, but ſuffocated thoſe ſuper-ſeminated <hi>Tares</hi> of contentions, how ſoon would it have cut off the occaſions of thoſe inhumane ſtrivings? nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would that black ſpirit of the Abyſſe have drawn men even from the <hi>Altar,</hi> to run to the <hi>ſword,</hi> which they indifferently thruſt into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of the neareſt <hi>Relations;</hi> after which followed ſo many cryes and lamentations, with ſuch images of death ſtill flying before our eyes, as
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:111621:32"/>were able to wound the heart with compaſſion, yea to move the moſt unnatural rage.</p>
            <p>Hence it is, that the godly evapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate into ſighs, and the convulſed world ſeems to mourn, with the ſad ſence and apprehenſion of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching <hi>judgement.</hi> And ſurely he that now revels it in <hi>greatneſſe,</hi> he that ſits idle amidſt the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints and mourning of the Church, muſt needs be infuſcated with the ſooty vapors of an inſenſible heart. Yea, hard are thoſe ears which bow not to the ſad relation of our long bleeding miſeries; and hirder thoſe eyes which can behold them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the moiſt teſtimonies of ſorrow. The Land grieveth for many horrid <hi>ſins;</hi> and may we not juſtly feat, leaſt <hi>Providence</hi> [ſo often provoked by our renewed treſpaſſes] will caſt us out as a <hi>prey</hi> to our enemies, or that the Sun of righteouſneſs may go down in our dayes?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:111621:33"/>
It were to enter into a vaſt La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byrinth of diſcourſes and reaſons to repreſent at this time thoſe vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blaſts of pernicious doctrine, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agitated by factious whirlewinds, ſince we may behold on the ſtage of the Church ſuch a horrible ſphere of Monſters, and Tempeſts, bloody Cornets, and Arms of fire [as the <hi>mali genii</hi> of ſeducing <hi>ſpirits</hi>] cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing ſo formidable a growth, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate our hopes, and undermine our happineſſe.</p>
            <p>The higheſt ſuperſpection and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilancy being therefore now more then ever requiſite to preſerve that <hi>truth</hi> which God hath eſpouſed to himſelf, and which we find the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil in all <hi>Ages</hi> to have raiſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to diſparage, diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and oppoſe, yea (if poſſbly) to over-throw, in the rooting out of the Miniſtry, and Profeſſors there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as being a ſpiritual Engine to batter down his Kingdom.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:111621:33"/>
Neither do the preſent contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances of thoſe (who I fear have long deceived the world with a laborious <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> ſince under the veil of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> are concealed ſuch flagitious and dangerous <hi>Tenents</hi>) ſeem to happen by humane deſignment, but as <hi>Cockatrise</hi> eggs, long ſince hatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by that old <hi>ſerpent,</hi> whoſe king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom drawing to an end, and having but a ſhort time to reign, there's hopes theſe ſpirits and Emiſſaries (who reſemble the wooden Dove of <hi>Archytas</hi> the Philoſopher, which flew by engines, whilſt they had their operation, and ſoared in the air, but ſo ſoon as they ceaſed, it trailed the wing on the earth) will not long infeſt the air with their ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liginous breath.</p>
            <p>And that God [who draweth light out of the boſom of darkneſs, and oftentimes ſuffereth not things vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to be long laſtin:] will (after we have profited by the experience
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:111621:34"/>of our evils) diſperſe thoſe amazing tumults, and prevent the growth of that <hi>Atheiſm</hi> which everywhere abounds, and threatneth ruine to his <hi>wayes,</hi> as if ſome hidden poiſon had envaded the land.</p>
            <p>All humane affairs are then only ſeated in the beſt ſtation of <hi>felicity,</hi> when they rejoyce in concord, pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and unity of Religion, it being an ill kind of ſolace for one man to compute his happineſſe by the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of anothers grief. And moſt miſerable are they of all men, who cannot be happy but by the miſeries of another. To what purpoſe is it to hold <hi>flowers</hi> to the noſtrils, when the body is parched and waſted with a violent <hi>feaver?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heat (in the opinion of ſome) doth more hurt then the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind; and ſtony ſpirits are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the moſt efficacious. And who ſees not that our <hi>Proteſtant</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:111621:34"/>have ever been the cauſe of our adverſaries rejoycings?</p>
            <p>As the ſweeteſt <hi>influences</hi> are thoſe which cauſe the ſweeteſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects in total nature; and not ſpark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Flames,</hi> but inviſible <hi>heats</hi> uſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ually melt hard metal; ſo who ſeeth not that ſilence and peace (which are the two manſions of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience) are of much more worth, then all the queſtions which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindle <hi>diviſions?</hi> the beſt doctrine being that which beſt knoweth how to cement up concord.</p>
            <p>But it hath been our unhappineſſe of late that in the great viciſſitude of things, evil minds have too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten intervened, which vitiated the Councels, retarded the endeavors, and diverted the intentions of ſuch who had a righter aim towards the advancement of the truth, then ſuch as were hurried into arms by a blind violence of ſpirit [not ſo much for love of juſtice as greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:111621:35"/>of revenge] and under the vail of <hi>Religion,</hi> labored to hide flagiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and damnable <hi>exceſſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Caeſari. in Dialog.] Caeſarius</hi> (a Geeek Author) ſaith, that Mill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones having no corn to grind, ſtrike fire one on another. And hath not the want of employment, with particular reflections on gain, profit, and preferment, interpos'd diſſentions not onely among the neereſt <hi>friends,</hi> but often times a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Religious?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againſt the unnaturalneſs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, we find an eminent example in the magnanimity of <hi>David,</hi> who could ſcarce be induced to a juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of his ſon <hi>Abſolom,</hi> though forcing his way unto his Fathers Throne through blood and rapine, untill <hi>Joab</hi> had diſſipated that lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guidneſſe of his gentle minde. And ſo deteſtable an undertaking was it held in thoſe who were brethren by the bonds of Nature and Religion,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:111621:35"/>to ſorfeit all civil reſpects to the rage of war, as that (if we take a review of the old Teſtament) we ſhall find though there were many and bitter diſcords, many tumults, many wars, yet they were ever againſt thoſe who had collapſed into foul and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent <hi>idolatry,</hi> and the worſhip of the <hi>Gentiles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8. (in whoſe heart God had locked up the Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imes of the beſt <hi>Policy</hi> in the world) invires us to be all of one mind, to love as brethren, to be pitiful and courteous. And we find our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.1.) to be called a <hi>Rod,</hi> and a <hi>Branch,</hi> to correct ſome, and to comfort o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but is never termed a <hi>ſword</hi> to kill and deſtroy. Oh that the thoughts hereof would cut off all further occaſions of inhumane ſtrivings! did our Saviour after he had triumphed over death ſalute his diſciples with the ſweet and amiable
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:111621:36"/>name of <hi>peace?</hi> Did the Apoſtles afterwards beautifie the entrance of their Epiſtles with it? Is it with this that the Angels rejoyce, and juſt men are delighted? And is it this only which tranſmits comfort to the weak, eaſe to the troubled, upon which all wiſhes are bent, in which all people are bleſſed? and muſt it not needs be an <hi>object</hi> full of bitter anguiſh to ſee a Nation worried to ruine by fraternal <hi>diſcords,</hi> which <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath eſpouſed by a particular election to himſelf? What doth it advantage diſconſolate man, to be freed from the expectations of a greedy enemy, by being rifled and impoveriſhed by thoſe of his own Nation?</p>
            <p>If a watchful eye abides in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ever active, never weary, but perpetually contemplates the deeds of men, and equally diſpenſeth to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veryone his deſervings [and who ſees not that Gods eye is as quickſighted
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:111621:36"/>in the diſcerning of hearts, as his hand is weighty in the chaſtiſements of crimes?] ſurely it is to feared that the Iron hand of provoked juſtice will fall heavy on contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſouls, who purſued others into diſorder; ſince where <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and love findes no habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, where (as in the war <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> raiſed againſt <hi>Magnentius</hi>) the Croſſe is oppoſed [in Arms] againſt the Croſſe, where Chriſtians (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getful of their covenant, forgetful of their name, and unmindful of their Relations) thus rage, one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another, there is either no Government, or ſuch as borders up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ruine.</p>
            <p>It is obſerved in Hiſtory for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Ages,</hi> that the wounds from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven have on all ſides faln on thoſe who have ſought to caſt the Apple of diſcord into the houſe of God; the wind blown from their mouth hath returned on their heads, ſince it
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:111621:37"/>is fit iniquity ſhould firſt kill it ſelf with its own poiſon; diſcords may for a time (indeed) increaſe with a prodigious fertility, &amp; thoſe thrones which are eſtabliſhed upon wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and cemented with blood, may for a time ſubſiſt with wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (God having appointed rods of his fury for our chaſtiſement) but have they not at laſt been tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured themſelves with thoſe pains and furies which they raiſed againſt others? Had it not been better they had put their hand; on <hi>Thornes</hi> then on the <hi>Pearls</hi> of a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme?</p>
            <p>God ſometimes (indeed) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits darkneſſe to execute its power upon the light, and the impious to perſecute the juſt (who every day drown a part of their life in their <hi>Tears</hi>) to render them the more glorious by their ſufferings; but that at laſt he takes their cauſe in hand, and overwhelms all humane
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:111621:37"/>policy in a crudity of undigeſted deſigns, let a <hi>Julian</hi> witneſs, whoſe greateſt deſign againſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, being the deſtroying of Learning, and the ſubſiſtence of the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> was blaſted from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in the midſt of his blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</p>
            <p>And though men of the ſame temper, may not meet with the like end, whom God oftentimes makes to die ſlowly by ſome ſtrange malady, and more lingring ſtroaks, rendering them the ſpectators of their own diſhonor, and their own funerals [as we ſee in <hi>Herod, Tiberius,</hi> and others] yet how ſuddainly have we ſeen many great ones of the world (luxuriating in their Glories, and made wanton by felicity) diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantled of them both? how often doth the Cypreſs diſappoint the Laurel, and an inconcocted ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of fortune obſtruct all the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:111621:38"/>of the conquerer, to whom no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was once thought wanting but immortality?</p>
            <p>How many Conquerours have we ſeen to ſtand over the ruins of the oppreſſed (being themſelves waſted by the expence of blood and ſtrength) who have been often near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er their Tombs, then their Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs, their Funerals, then their Palms? And (when contemplating the principal object of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light) have they ſound any thing to entertain their curioſity, but a forced and unpleaſant laughter?</p>
            <p>So hard is it to row in the ſtream of the world, where God conducts not the veſſel, whoſe juſt anger al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes follows ſinners at the heels, onely waits untill the offering be fat to ſacrifice it. When God intends to abandon man for his demerits, and to ſacrifice him to his Juſtice, he leaves him to himſelf, and to the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:111621:38"/>wiſhes of his own heart; he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits him to ſatiate ambition or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge; to entangle himſelf under ſome great deſign under the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of honor and Juſtice, and (although he be vicious) gives him ſucceſſes, and incomparable proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, that puff up his heart, and make him preſume upon his own conduct; he takes from him the true taſte of <hi>divine</hi> things, and (if he have any faithful Councellors) ſlatterers, and enchanters poſſeſſe their place. If any evil affright him, or any ſcourge from heaven overwhelm him, he is made believe it is but a natural thing, untill at laſt he be put upon the Pinacle of his higheſt dignities, and the moſt mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent negotiations, which preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitate him into <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate ſenſe, which is the laſt ſtep that one makes to enter into hell.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:111621:39"/>
I ſhould not have ſo much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed on this ſubject, but that ſome hidden poiſon ſeems of late to have infected many, and engaged them in blind and unexpected diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions concerning that great que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of <hi>propriety</hi> [ſo much contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted throughout the world] the which (as <hi>Archeſilaus</hi> hath long ſythence held forth) is a buſineſſe ſo perplexed, as never to be determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, being the confuſion of things and fortunes, neceſſarily engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring continually jars and endleſs diſagreements; and that a cruel preparation of mind to revenge, an implacable diſpoſition, a barbarous luſt to rebell, a ſecret ſpeculation of Lordly Dominion, and other ſuch cauſes have too plainly appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in thoſe who conſider not that it is more eaſie to raiſe troubles, then to moderate them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:111621:39"/>
Neither (indeed) are any way acquainted with the converſation of thoſe, who at the Nativity of our bleſſed Saviour ſang <hi>Anthems</hi> of Peace, which is the greateſt and moſt excellent gift of the divine indulgence, and from which flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the opulency of Kingdoms, the accumulation of all temporal bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, and the moſt active vigor of all functions in the body Politick. Whereas on the contrary, where concord is diſſipated, and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larms of war beſiege mens ears (whoſe ingreſſe is troubleſome, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe doubtful, and the egreſſe for the moſt part deplorable) there preſently inſueth a convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and direful decay of all the members; and audacity (finding it ſelf diſengaged from the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Laws) runneth head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into all variety of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:111621:40"/>
And hence is it, that the ſtreats are often times not onely covered with dead bodies, and the little children ſighing out their laſt breath upon the bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carcaſſes of deceaſing Parents, that ſtrangers poſſeſſe the heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, and inrich themſelves with the ſpoils of the ruined and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, but that the Temples have been handled as the object of all reproaches, and thoſe veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of glory which ſerved for the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of the Lord, have been taken away by impiated hands; that the moſt ſacred things are violenced, and the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane licenced, the nocent and innocent are involved in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of a ſad and promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Cataſtrophe.</p>
            <p>Surely as he would be too much in love with life, to be willing
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:111621:40"/>to ſpare, and keep it in the loſſe of the true Religion, ſo muſt he deeds be ſorry that ever he entred into the world, when he conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the time, to which God had reſerved his Age, to ſee the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſters and deſolation of a place or people abandoned to the fury of Rapinous hands, and the prophana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the impious, to ſee raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Harpys</hi> [fatted with humane ruines] to ruſh into thoſe well fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered Neſts which they built not; to ſee whole Families loaded with injuries, and the props of build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to tremble with loud <hi>blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> yea to behold ſuch fatal Comets which ſhall portend no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but fire and ſword to Church and State.</p>
            <p>What an Edict do we finde pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by an Apoſtle inveſted with Thunder, and lightning? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.6.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:111621:41"/>And were he ſent again into the world by Providence, what would he imagine, who then wanted patience to ſee a controverſie [about a field perhaps, or a houſe] if he ſhould now behold thoſe that claim the title of the faithful, to oppoſe not a houſe or City one againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but even ſtrive to precipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate whole Provinces, yea a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into Rapes, diſorders, and priviledged Plunders? He that would not ſuffer <hi>one brother to go to law with another,</hi> but rather <hi>to ſuffer wrong and ſuſtain fraud,</hi> would he have countenanced ſuch inhumane ſpectacles, with a Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of allowance, as now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear viſible in the face of this Age?</p>
            <p>And if our Saviour enjoyned a removal of all ſcandals from his
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:111621:41"/>Kingdom, dooming the Authors thereof to have a Mill-ſtone hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about their Necks, and their bodies caſt into the Sea, what will become of thoſe who through their own ambitious ends [as if God were bound to define all things according to their ſenſe, and will] fall into diviſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, withdraw from each other, and cenſure one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother? Wo, and alas! will bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren forgetful of their Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, forgetfull of their Name, and unmindfull of their Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, thus rage, contemne, yea deſtroy thoſe which they ought not to hate!</p>
            <p>Will not the people, ſeeing ſo many <hi>Religions</hi> held forth (as they think) and ſo many ſeverall wayes and minds, think it is as good be of none, as adventure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:111621:42"/>ſo many? What juſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of offence will hereby be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the ignorant, to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, and ſuch as are yet unſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in their judgement, when (ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther through pride, or petulan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy they ſhall ſee men change their opinions which a while ago they ſeemed to be ſo zealous for? doth not this make them think that the reſt may be as uncertain as thoſe?</p>
            <p>Surely, its an extream rage and furious diſpair which thus expects nothing but the height of <hi>evils</hi> for its Remedy; and how great a ſcandal the Lives of ſuch Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors will at laſt throw upon the <hi>Church</hi> of God, I wiſh the ſad experience of the times may not too plainly manifeſt; many (no doubt) having been kept off from the practice, and approving of a
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:111621:42"/>godly life, through the unhappy differences among our ſelves.</p>
            <p>But that which is the ſoul of misfortune, is the great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of that high <hi>Calling,</hi> for which the Apoſtle <hi>thought none ſufficient.</hi> It is not denied but that God can make his Oracles ſpeak without a voice [and Oh what a great thing is nothing in the hands of God, who can teach without a School, and in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment change ignorants into Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and Peſants into Prophets!] But what? ſhall we neglect the ordinary means appointed in his word to lead us to him? What can we expect from a Phyſitian that diſcourſeth of war, or a bare Scholar treating of the ſecret de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of Princes? No more may we look for from thoſe late <hi>Chaplains</hi> of Satans ordering, who
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:111621:43"/>pretend good to do miſchief, and act his part in the attire of an Angel.</p>
            <p>The ſpirit alſo is promiſed to lead us into all truth, but not by fanatick <hi>Enthuſiaſmas.</hi> The ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God ſpeaks to us in and by [but not <hi>beſides,</hi> or beyond] the Scripture; to hold therefore extraordinary <hi>Revelations</hi> [where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by things were formerly made known to the Prophets] or to pretend to immediate inſpirations without the word, is a deluſion as monſtruous as deteſtable, and ought to be rejected as an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Satan, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.2. and as the uſual pretences of Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, againſt whoſe fanatical con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, God hath ſufficiently fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned us, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.1, <hi>Galathians</hi> 1.8.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:111621:43"/>
The Scripture being written for our learning, we are command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there to <hi>ſearch,</hi> as the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit of Life and power of God unto ſalvation. Of whom we are not taught to enquite at the <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> of our luſts and Phantaſies, nor to be led by <hi>opinions</hi> of our own framing. And ſurely the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the Mongrel-blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, <hi>Levit.</hi> 24. ſhould make all conſcionable men afraid how they adventure this way, to make bold with Gods ſacred Name, leaſt perchance (like the ſons of <hi>Sceva</hi>) they meet with ſome mad devils to whip them from their preſumptious folly.</p>
            <p>And yet [to the ſad reproach of a ſinfull Nation, may it be ſpoken] none are now adayes more cried up, then ſuch as were never brought up in the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:111621:44"/>Schools of the Prophets, nor lawfully ordained to the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,</hi> which is now ſo commonly ſlandered by our <hi>[Jeſuited]</hi> Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, telling the people that their <hi>Prieſts</hi> have deluded them, that they have falſified the word [which, alas! they themſelves have too fouly wreſted] yea ſome of them have been pleaſed to call the greateſt cheat could be put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>But let the manifeſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from heaven upon <hi>Vzziah</hi> ſerve (among many other inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which might be produced) as an example of terror; to ſuch ſecular Powers, as will incroah upon <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> and break the barriers that Providence hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed, for the differencing of the ſpiritual and temporal autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Neither let the priviledge
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:111621:44"/>of Times (though the barres of impudence ſeem broken down) be made a colour to excuſe any from Sacrilegious boldneſs, who min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle myſteriouſly divine reaſons with their own humane Fancies, which as Queen, and Governeſs ought to be chief Ruler, and not ſuffragant, in ſo ſacred and holy a Subject.</p>
            <p>Beſides, is it not an unſeemly thing to ſee the ſacred volume of our <hi>Belief-myſteries,</hi> toſſed up and down, and plaid withall in every ſhop, or kitching? and that thoſe divine <hi>Oracles</hi> which (here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore) have been accounted <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries,</hi> ſhould be thus abuſed, by ſuch as go about ſowing of <hi>ſchiſm,</hi> ſetting of <hi>Errors,</hi> and ſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>faction.</hi> Surely, ſo ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and venerable a ſtudy, ſhould not thus tumultuarily be
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:111621:45"/>diſcuſſed, Gods word being a Hiſtory religiouſly to be adored, aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully feared, and not fabulouſly reported.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Mahometans,</hi> and almoſt all Nations, are with reverence wedded unto the bare language wherein their Religion had originally been conceived; all change and tranſlation having been directly forbidden. And one of our <hi>Grecian</hi> Hiſtorians, doth (not without appearance of reaſon) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe his Age, for ſo much as the ſecrets of Chriſtrain Religion were ſo farre diſpenced in publike, as that every man might at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure diſpute of it, and at ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome vent his opinion of the ſame.</p>
            <p>And certainly it ſhould be a great ſhame to us, who by the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:111621:45"/>unſpeakable mercy of God enjoy the pure, and ſacred <hi>Myſteries</hi> of piety, to ſuffer the ſame to be profaned by an erratical and circumforaneous motion, in the mouthes of ignorant and popular people, ſeeing the very Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles interdicted <hi>Socrates, Plato,</hi> and the wiſeſt among them, to meddle, enquire, or ſpeak of things committed to the Prieſts of <hi>Delphos;</hi> yea did flatly inhibite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves the uſe of the Name of their god in all their vulgar and familiar diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
            <p>It was not long ſince accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a great fault for <hi>Miniſters</hi> to intermeddle with lay-Offices; yet how many of <hi>Jeroboams</hi> Prieſts have we now ſtarted up among us who continue in the civil <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</hi> yet think themſelves; able to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:111621:46"/>charge that of the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> not conſidering that there are no <hi>ſins,</hi> which God doth puniſh more rigorouſly, nor ſpeedily, then thoſe which are committed, againſt devotion and piety.</p>
            <p>How ſuddainly did that King finde a Leproſie riſe from the high Prieſts? Yea how was <hi>Ely</hi> the chief Prieſt buried in the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines of his own houſe, for the ſacriledge of his children, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any conſideration of thoſe long ſervies which he had perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at the Tabernacle! We find our Saviour alſo not to take up the ſcourge againſt naughty Judges, Uſurers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but drives out <hi>the buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and ſellers of the Temple,</hi> Joh. 2. as if to commit a <hi>ſin</hi> againſt Gods Altar, the remedy would grow deſperate; and ſhould there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore warn us, as to keep our ſelves from Simonies, from Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:111621:46"/>and irrevetence in Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, ſo from abuſing the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and worſhip of God, without a warrantable Call; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he can have no excuſe, who makes his Judge his witneſſe.</p>
            <p>He that thus builds without God, doth but demoliſh; and whoſoever thinks this way to make any great encreaſe, ſhall finde nothing but ſterility. And may not the voice of God hence cry aloud unto us in his Temple, Can my ſoul participate of your counſels, or my glory come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your company, ſince whileſt you erect Altars to me, you offer your vows to your own luſts? you not <hi>ſacrifice,</hi> but <hi>ſin,</hi> you bend your knees but not your hearts; Deceive not the world, neither make falſe boaſtings in my worſhip, except you manacle your own
<pb n="06" facs="tcp:111621:47"/>paſſions, and tame your deceitful minds.</p>
            <p>We have of late (indeed) glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beheld the devout multitude crouding the Churches to pour fourth their wiſhes. How often have we ſeen the Religious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate in the Sanctuary, implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the aid of heaven by fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent ſighs, and importuning di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine providence with unwearied prayers? But alas! may not God ſay unto us [when we are even partaking of his ſacred myſteries] how hath the blood of many mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable men been ſhed, for whom I have ſhed my blood? whileſt you cry to me, do not thouſands, of Orphans and widdows cry to behold the dead carcaſſes of their husbands and parents? you ſeem to kiſſe my head, but kick at my members; you flatter me with
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:111621:47"/>your Faſtings, but perſecute me with Arms. Your ſwords reak with the blood of one another; you preſent your ſelves ſuppliants before me, but raiſe contentions abroad. You have the voice of <hi>Jacob,</hi> but the hands of <hi>Eſau;</hi> yea, whileſt you ſmell of incenſe, it is by your means that whole Townes are turned into ſmoak.</p>
            <p>And I wiſh it may never be laid to the charge of any of their laſt account, who ſhould have compoſed the Nation when it was diſunited with diſcords, and endeavored to reconcile the irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular tumults of the Church, that they have abandoned themſelves to the infamous Councils of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiavel,</hi> and their own ſelf-inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts; this being not that wiſdom which (to uſe the words of the Apoſtle) <hi>deſcendeth from above,</hi>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:111621:48"/>but is carnal, <hi>ſenſual</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viliſh.</p>
            <p>Sythence from hence proceeds the dulling of that <hi>two-edged ſword,</hi> which divides between the bones, and the marrow, and by the power whereof blaſphemies, ſacriledges, hereſies, and impieties would have vaniſhed, and all have been ſcattered; Laws would not have been ſilent among ſwords, the honour and worſhip of God ſo much contemned, the hypocrites have the uncontrolled liberty of ſpeaking, poor miſled and ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſouls would not have been made believe they ſin in not tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> and their <hi>Calling,</hi> as a humane invention, meerly introduced to uphold car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall intereſt, nor <hi>Wolves</hi> ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly have infected the <hi>Tents</hi> of the ſhepherds.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:111621:48"/>
Is not this to be wiſe without God? And doth it not hence al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo happen that in ſtead of profit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the School of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and in the Doctrine of ſo good a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, we are bold only for the world, and timorous in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of God? If a falſhood be to be averred, if a revenge be to be put forward [even to the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of blood] If lawful <hi>Powers</hi> be to be reſiſted; if laws both di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and humane be to be ſpoken againſt, there wants neither bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe nor confidence; but (though all men are naturally ſtirred up with the reſentment of a <hi>Divinity</hi>) yet emulation doth ſo often mingle it ſelf with <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> as that ſome ſeek their own glory in lifting up that of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, and (contray to the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the eternal wiſdom it ſelf) accord the devil of <hi>proper intereſt</hi>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:111621:49"/>with the <hi>Maximes</hi> of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> by ſerving two Maſters.</p>
            <p>And doth it not proceed from the falſe and ſcandalous lives of ſuch profeſſors, that the mindes of pious people are offended, that the ſad harmony of our enemies jubilations is? See how they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agree and deſtroy one another! and the ſcoffing tongues of the notoriouſly wicked are ſharpened againſt our <hi>Religion;</hi> that we are made gazing ſtocks to <hi>others,</hi> and are become formidable to our ſelves; whereas, would we but make God to march in the head of our affairs, who is the ſourſe of all good ſucceſſes, how ſoon would Religion deface the ſpots which ſo eaſily ſlide into our lives!</p>
            <p>Surely either the <hi>Religion</hi> we
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:111621:49"/>profeſſe accuſeth our <hi>errours,</hi> or elſe we the Profeſſors accuſe our <hi>Religion.</hi> Where <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, Love finds no habitation; and needs muſt there be a heap of groſs <hi>impieties,</hi> where there is an oblivion of the greateſt <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies;</hi> needs muſt our <hi>Errors</hi> turn to <hi>hereſies,</hi> when they are practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by deſign, and obſtinacy, and overtake us not by ſurprize, but poſſeſſe us with a reſolute opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the deciſions of the Church. Are not theſe <hi>ſpots in our Feaſts,</hi> ſeeming rather to be the actings of men exiled from God, and lawleſſe in the world, and of ſuch as (through the beat of a miſtaken <hi>zeal</hi>) think to meet <hi>Jeſus</hi> among the engagements and purſuit of worldly <hi>intereſts,</hi> who is onely to be found in the Temple, in his Ordinances, and the communion of his Saints?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:111621:50"/>
Here onely is the Sanctuary of reſt, where wearied ſouls may lay their heads; here ſhall we be ſure to meet with comfortable embraces, and from his mouth (whoſe Laws are eſtabliſhed upon foundations ſtronger then the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of heaven, and earth) ſhall we receive the excellent <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,</hi> and cleareſt Revelations of <hi>eternity.</hi> And when men have once left this <hi>Truth</hi> [their onely quiet home] they will take up their lodging [all <hi>errors</hi> being near of kin] under any root or opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion which hath the leaſt ſhadow of probability; ſuch an ignorant zeal being too blind to go right, and too active to ſtand ſtill, and like <hi>raſae tabulae</hi> or unſealed wax, ready to take any impreſſion.</p>
            <p>And however ſome may poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly pretend holineſs towards God,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:111621:50"/>
               <hi>for the ſetting up of their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings as ſigns in the midſt of Gods Sanctuary, and for the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down at once the carved work thereof with axes and hammers,</hi> Pſal. 74.4, 6. and at laſt root up all that they may take the Houſes of God into their own poſſeſſion, and like brutiſh <hi>doegs,</hi> fall upon Gods Prieſts, that they may have the greateſt ſhare in the plunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their means; yet ſurely, this their pretended goodneſs ſeems but as <hi>the morning cloud, and as the early dew will paſſe a-away,</hi> Hoſ. 6.4. ſeeing the ſtaves of Beauty are hereby broken in pieces, and the entire bands of Chriſtian Truth, Order, and Peace, quite cut aſunder, even to the making ſhipwrack of faith and a good conſcience, and the extream hazard of our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal ſouls.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:111621:51"/>
O let us not thus be flattered into a ſecurity of our exceſſes, ſince the whole head is ſick, the whole heart is heavy, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſafe, nothing is pleaſant among ſuch calamities, where the worſt of evils is the rejoycing, and where the eyes of <hi>Truth</hi> have been of late put out by the duſt and rubbiſh which hath been made through the fall of ſo great and ancient a Fabrick!</p>
            <p>And who ere they be that ſtrive againſt the peaceable wiſhes of the Church, by railing at, revil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and undermining the pillars thereof, by reproaching their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, decrying their office, by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating and exclaiming againſt their maintenance, by ſupporting and countenancing Errors and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, before their wholeſomer Doctrine; and whereby to ruin
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:111621:51"/>them and their Religion (by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a wide gap for blaſphemy, Atheiſm and prophaneneſs) let them alſo take heed, leaſt ſome grievous hand fall upon them from heaven; and that (meeting with unhappy events in all their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings) their life becomes not troubleſome, and their death not doubtful.</p>
            <p>If we conſult with hiſtory, how various are the examples on ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hand, we ſhall not onely find a buſie <hi>Achitophel</hi> paid the juſt wages of his Traiterous Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels with an infamous halter; We ſhall not onely finde <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> (who thruſt his ſouldiers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Battels beyond the progreſſe of the Sunne, and the limits of the Sea) to periſh by poiſon from his own Domeſticks; neither <hi>Hannibal</hi> alone (who ſo long
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:111621:52"/>weaved the inextricable web of war) to ſhorten the date of his contempts with voluntary poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; but ſurely all thoſe who thus think to pleaſe themſelves in an ill-rectified devotion and formal profeſſion, will prove no other than barren Trees, which make a great noiſe, and never beare Fruit. And how ſad will their account be, who thus prick their fingers whileſt they are gathering of <hi>Roſes?</hi> How ſad will it be with us, when we ſhall [for thus betraying the moſt <hi>holy things</hi>] curſe the womb that bare us, and the breaſts that gave us ſuck; the Church that Chriſtened us, and the Miniſter that Catechized us; and when we ſhall beſhrew the day that ever we heard a good Sermon? Alas that our miſery ſhould be height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from our <hi>means</hi> of being once happy! That we ſhould bewail
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:111621:52"/>our very <hi>knowledge,</hi> and repent us even of our <hi>Grace!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O how will they then bluſh, when that (<hi>Jer.</hi> 23.24.) God (who fills heaven and earth) ſhall have a Candle in every mans boſom [even their own conſciences] who ſtrive to make their <hi>ſins</hi> look ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly, by making them well-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured, who embrace <hi>ſchiſm</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of <hi>Truth,</hi> and too often take complexion for <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion?</hi> will it not be eaſier for the Gentiles which know not God, than ſuch as thus worſhip him? O ſtrange deluſion to take the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt vice for the greateſt vertue! all the out-ſide of our godlineſſe this way rendring us but the worſe before God!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hereſie</hi> [the key of <hi>Atheiſm</hi>] may for a time (indeed) make
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:111621:53"/>arrows of any wood, to hit the marks of their intereſt, and like a fawning ſervant, be ever ready to obſerve his Maſters will in ſuch ill offices wherein his own advantage concurreth: Though all at laſt will be conſumed like A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bortives in their birth, and no otherwiſe ſtead them than as Woods and Foreſts ſhelter Theeves, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to cover their crimes.</p>
            <p>Since he that this way thinks to pacifie <hi>Divine</hi> Majeſty, inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it; He that with <hi>Saul</hi> offers up the golden mountains of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety and injuſtice, doth but offer to God the Sacrifices of diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, which defile rather then adorn the Altats of God, ſeeing they onely garniſh the ambition of man. But as peaceable diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions ſometimes ſurfet of reſt, becauſe the natural inclination to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:111621:53"/>change, makes felicity it ſelf to become tedious; ſo troubleſome heads alwayes account quietneſſe their greateſt enemy, no way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that our approach to God ought to be a fixed, a purpoſed and ſetled Action, to which our heart ſhould be ever ſo ſolemnly adjoyned; neither ought he to be commixed with any of our <hi>Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> but with an awfull reverence, and attention full of horror and reſpect.</p>
            <p>And though there are many <hi>Endyminions</hi> to be found who embrace the Moon, whoſe hearts are ever and anon wheeling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout in endleſſe Labyrinths, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaged with changeable <hi>fancies,</hi> and whoſe ſpirits are perpetually attended with turbulencies, and gnawn with the itch of novelty; yet let all our ends and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:111621:54"/>be recollected in God as beams in the Sun.</p>
            <p>It is the nature of Quick-ſilver to tremble up and down, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver leaveth untill it hath found gold wherewith to mingle; ſo the heart of man boundeth and leap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth here and there in all its trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and diſturbances, there being nothing but ebbs and floods, untill ſuch time as it is united to its Creatour (the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of all repoſe.) And let all ſuch know who ſeem to catch the world with a hook, who rejoyce in their own crime as if it were a vertue, and make Sacrifices with the inſtruments of miſchief, who judge of happineſs by the multitude of <hi>Preys,</hi> and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no other God but their good fortune, that however they think to proſper in their own i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginations,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:111621:54"/>and worldly affairs, being yet inwardly diſunited from the eternal wiſdom of God, they are no other than <hi>Icaruſſes</hi> who ſeek to counterfeit Birds with waxen wings; the leaſt ray pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the throne of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, being able to burn them, and make their heigth ſerve to no other uſe than to render their fall the more remarkable; or like the golden precipices of <hi>Heliogabalus</hi> which were not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed but to make his <hi>ruine</hi> the more memorable.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid, the very ſeathers of the Eagle are ſo imperious that they will not mix with the Plum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of other Birds, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming them; and ſhall we think to mingle God, who is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible wiſdom, a riches inexhauſtible, and a purity infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:111621:55"/>with our feeble pretenſion, which have frenzy for beginnins, miſery for inheritance, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purity for ornament?</p>
            <p>If we are not to appropriate to our ſelves ſacred Gold nor Silver, neither to transferre to prophane uſes what hath been dedicated to God (as we find expreſſed both in Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Laws) how do we offend God (who hath granted us a Spirit of Gold, yea (I may ſay) a heart of Gold, when he waſhed and regenerated us by the ſpirit of Baptiſm) when we therewith mingle the weak <hi>fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> of our own brain! And how far are we from rendring to God what is due to him, when we make uſe of our heart as a veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of abomination, fraughting it with the Chimeraes of our fond imaginations, and planting no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:111621:55"/>therein, but the petty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of our own glory, and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious humors, as an Altar where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we daily preſent the beſt part of our ſacrifice!</p>
            <p>We find that the worſt of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, Mezentius</hi> could finde no greater cruelty on earth then to tie a dead body to a <hi>living;</hi> and ſhall we faſten thoughts of our dead and languiſhing mindes with God who is nothing but life and truth? Surely, its high time for us to leave the giddy fancies of the world, to behold Beauties and lights of divine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, unleſs we mean to Regiſter our defects in the Calander of <hi>eternity.</hi> Shall we preſcribe limits to the Almighty? ſhall we thus lay continual ſiege unto his power by our own weak reaſons [no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then dreams, or vanity?] or
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:111621:56"/>ſhall we ſubject the <hi>Idea's</hi> of him who hath made both us and our knowledge, to the vain and weak appearances of our underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing?</p>
            <q>
               <l>Quid juvat hoc?</l>
               <l>Ocurvae in terris animae &amp; caleſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um inanes!</l>
            </q>
            <p>What do we herein leſſe, than amuſe the curioſity of our mind, by ſeeking to feed it with gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the raw bones of our own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions?</p>
            <p>Let us no longer then make warre againſt heaven, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract from Gods glory, by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring our own <hi>Fancies</hi> to his prejudice. <hi>Religion</hi> (like the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſe, all the members where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of mutually love and embrace) is united and collected within it
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:111621:56"/>ſelf; how ought we then to take heed of diſ-joynting it through <hi>Schiſme,</hi> and the diſordinate love of our own wild and wavering conceits, which carry with them ſo much of infidelity, of contempt of God, yea of down right <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſm!</hi> Yea which ordinarily makes our beſt ſeeming perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, the more deteſtable by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuating with ſuch ſubtilties, and pretexts of holineſs, as if it were moſt devout, this being not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſimple Tyranny, but a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, and (through its exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance) deſcendeth to the worſt of deformities!</p>
            <p>Surely, if through our weakneſs we once corrupt and adulterate the eſſence of Truth, Oh into what a point of preſumptuous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolency will not our blindneſſe carry us? How ſhall we ſooth our
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:111621:57"/>ſelves into ſome illumination, which will really prove but an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregious dotage? and thereby ſo involve our ſelves in a miſt, and grope in the dark, as if <hi>Truth</hi> were gotten into ſome dungeon, which our ſhallow apprehenſions could not fathom.</p>
            <p>Its but vain to implore Gods power in a bad cauſe. Man ought to have an unpolluted ſoul, and abſolutely free from all vicious paſſions (at leaſt wiſe) in that moment he addreſſeth himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him; otherwiſe we our ſelves preſent him the rods to whip us withall; and in ſtead of redreſſing our fault, we redouble the ſame, by preſenting him with ſuch, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections as are fraught with ſin and irreverence, to whom only we ſhould ſue for grace and forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:111621:57"/>
If we pretend good, to do miſchief, and act the devils part in the attire of an Angel, what do we other then foſter the crime and the Judge in one and the ſame Manſion?</p>
            <p>And what is this but to lend nothing to devotion, but what might flatter our Paſſions, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven make that Religion to ſhrowd and foſter our vices, which it was ordained to root out? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he that thus calls God for his aſſiſtance, while he is engul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phed in <hi>ſinne,</hi> doth but like the <hi>Thief</hi> which called <hi>Juſtice</hi> for his aide, or thoſe that produce Divine Providence in witneſs of a lye.</p>
            <p>Let us no longer dare then to burn incenſe upon that Altar, to which we have no lawfull call;
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:111621:58"/>for which we finde a good Prince [otherwiſe] to carry the ſpots of his too much forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to his grave. Our heart being ruled, and our ſoul com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by faith, reaſon will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that we draw all other parts to the ſervice of God, according to their beſt power and faculty. Our <hi>ſinnes,</hi> though naturally tending downward as to their centre, do (through the too much preferring of our own inventions in Gods worſhip, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his holy preſcriptions) mount upwards by their cry; nothing but our <hi>ſighs</hi> and prayers being left us (as the beſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſounds) to drown their noiſe, that God may not hear them; and the pleading merits of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> with the loved lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of his blood, being the beſt way to ſilence the loud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:111621:58"/>of their cry, and divert the Judgement (otherwiſe) inevitably attending them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
